Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center Records, 1986-2011
Sophia Smith Collection
Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center records
1985-2011
Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center
MS526
31 boxes (15 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Women's health advocacy organization. The Records focus on NAWHERC's administration, funding, programs, studies, and work in coalition with other women's health, indigenous rights, environmental stewardship, and women of color organizations. Major topics found throughout these papers include Native American health and cultural survival, rights of indigenous peoples, alcoholism and other drug dependency problems, abortion and reproductive health, fetal alcohol syndrome, diabetes, breast cancer, HIV/AIDS, environmental toxins, sexually-transmitted diseases, and sexual and domestic violence. The Programs files document important conferences and gatherings sponsored and co-sponsored by NAWHERC, such as the HIV/AIDS Gatherings for Spiritual Leaders and Traditional Healers and the Native Women's Reproductive Rights Coalition which developed the Native Women's Reproductive Rights Agenda, and the Native Women's Leadership Training Program. Types of materials include correspondence, financial records, legal documents, news clippings, photographs, press releases, publications, studies and reports, and subject files.
In 1985 Charon Asetoyer, Clarence Rockboy, Everdale Song Hawk, Jackie Rouse, and Lorenzo Dion, a group of Native Americans living on or near the 40,000 acre Yankton Sioux Reservation in southeastern South Dakota, came together to form the Native American Community Board (NACB). NACB's goals are to improve the quality of life by addressing issues of health, education, land and water rights, and economic development of indigenous people. It is an independent non-profit, non-governmental organization that is not part of federally supported tribal government. NACB provides awareness of pertinent health issues; promotes community involvement in economic development; promotes better educational systems; coordinates urban, tribal, and state child welfare issues; and engages in activities to promote survival of culture and way of life, working on the local, national and international levels to reach these goals.
At the time of its formation, the unemployment rate on the reservation was eighty-five percent, seventy percent of adults over age forty suffered from diabetes, the infant mortality rate was five times the national average, and life expectancy on the reservation was just forty-five years.
After its 1986 incorporation as a non-profit, tax-exempt organization, NACB's first project was "Women and Children in Alcohol," a fetal alcohol syndrome program -- operated out of Asetoyer and Rockboy's basement -- which served to define the direction of the organization's subsequent health work. The project aimed to address, in Charon Asetoyer's words, "fetal alcohol syndrome and all of the residual issues related to it, because you get into children's issues, you get into education, you get into women's issues and needs. And you get into how women were treated who were chemically dependent and how their rights were being violated." (Voices of Feminism oral history, 2006, p. 27)
Inspired by a visit to the National Black Women's Health Project in Atlanta, Georgia, Asetoyer began to imagine a similar facility in her town, Lake Andes, South Dakota, that was more of a center than an office; a physical space where women and children could gather for self-help groups, tutoring, education, and nutrition demonstrations. In 1988 the NACB purchased a house at 810 High Street in Lake Andes and established the Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center (NAWHERC). The Center opened its doors in February of that year.
NAWHERC assists women and their families through direct services, public policy advocacy, and coalition building with indigenous women around the world. The Center is noted for its community-based research and publications, which have influenced policies and practices of the Indian Health Service and other agencies.
Under its treaty obligations, the U.S. government is required to provide free health care to all Native Americans living on reservations. This care is delivered via the Indian Health Service (IHS), a division of the U.S. Public Health Service. However, IHS is essentially a crisis care service.
NACB established NAWHERC to provide ongoing comprehensive community health education among Native Americans and to impact policy issues that affect indigenous women nationally and internationally. "The project is designed for women and children, based on a self-help philosophy, promoting individual and group involvement in the betterment of our lives as Native American people." (31 Oct 1988 NAWHERC press release)
NACB serves as the Board of Directors for NAWHERC, setting policy and monitoring its finances. As of 2006, the staff (including interns) numbered fourteen. The Resource Center is the operational headquarters for the majority of NACB's projects. It is funded primarily by private foundations and individual donors.
The first organization to do work on AIDS prevention and awareness in South Dakota, NAWHERC's "wholeness" programs focus on health education and prevention (including AIDS awareness, sexually-transmitted diseases, Ob-Gyn self-help, breast cancer awareness, nutrition, and fetal alcohol syndrome); support services (domestic abuse, Alcoholics Anonymous, and general support); adult learning (typing and computer skills); and child development (skill building, tutoring, computer education, and special needs services).
Early "social change and advocacy" work included conferences, fairs, community action to defeat a proposed landfill, bringing a discrimination case about misuse of federal funding for Native American children, and community gardens. Later NAWHERC worked to bring attention to sterilization abuse, and questioned the efficacy and safety of reproductive technologies such as Norplant and Depo-Provera, particularly as prescribed by the Indian Health Service (HIS).
Conceived as a center for wholeness and a place for promoting and facilitating social change, today NAWHERC gathers information on the health needs of indigenous women in the Aberdeen area of the IHS (North Dakota, South Dakota, Iowa, and Nebraska), provides referral services, runs a domestic violence shelter, and advocates native rights. The Center maintains programs on domestic violence, AIDS prevention, youth services, adult learning, Dakota language and culture, environmental awareness and action, fetal alcohol syndrome, nutrition, and reproductive health and rights.
Beginning in 1989 NAWHERC staff did intensive research and lobbying to maintain services by preventing the IHS from converting the local hospital into an outpatient-only facility. Its staff and interns went on to research and document IHS's reproductive health care, abortion, and sexual assault services and policies.
In 1990 NAWHERC co-sponsored the conference "Empowerment Through Dialogue: Native American Women and Reproductive Rights," which brought together women from eleven tribes to develop the Native Women's Reproductive Rights Agenda, and form of the Native Women's Reproductive Rights Coalition. As part of its AIDS Awareness and Prevention Program, NAWHERC also sponsored HIV/AIDS Gatherings for Spiritual Leaders and Traditional Healers beginning in the early 1990s.
In September of 1991, after a year-long legal battle over zoning, NAWHERC opened a shelter for battered women, a few blocks away from the Resource Center. The Lake Andes Women's Lodge provides women and their children with a safe place to escape domestic violence and sexual assault. Staff studied and also documented management of domestic violence cases in the county criminal justice system and, through its 2005 Domestic Violence Prevention Project, hired a probation officer with specialized training with domestic abuse offenders.
The 1993 Native American Women's Leadership Development Program partnered with two organizations on other reservations to strengthen infrastructure and provide technical assistance and training.
NAWHERC produced a group of studies and reports in the mid-1990s related to environmental issues impacting the local community, such as radon, herbicide and pesticide use, fly-ash contamination, and a proposed landfill.
Other programs include: Youth Services (including the Child Development Program and the Youth Wellness Program); the Adult Learning Program; the Environmental Awareness and Action Project; the Diabetic Nutrition Program; and the Fetal Alcohol Syndrome Awareness Program. NAWHERC also provides information about cancer prevention, reproductive health and rights, and educational scholarships. It administers a food pantry, sponsors community health fairs, published a newsletter titled Wicozanni Wowapi Good Health Newsletter (1985-), and later an email newsletter, Indigenous Women's Reproductive Watch (2008-)
Other publications include culturally sensitive nutrition education materials published in collaboration with the National Cancer Institute (1990-91), the Indigenous Women's Health Book, Within the Sacred Circle: Reproductive Rights, Environmental Health, Traditional Herbs and Remedies (2003), and a Teen Dating Violence Prevention Curriculum and Workbook for Native American Girls (2003)
For more information see the Center's web site at http://www.nativeshop.org/about-us.html
The Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center Records consist of 15 linear ft. dating from 1985 to 2008. Types of materials include correspondence, financial records, legal documents, news clippings, photographs, press releases, publications, studies and reports, and subject files.
The bulk of the records date from 1988 to 2003 and focus on NAWHERC's administration; funding, programs, studies, and work in coalition with other women's health, indigenous rights, environmental stewardship, and women of color organizations.
Major topics found throughout these papers include Native American health and cultural survival, rights of indigenous peoples, alcoholism and other drug dependency problems, abortion and reproductive health, fetal alcohol syndrome, diabetes, breast cancer, HIV/AIDS, environmental toxins, sexually-transmitted diseases, and sexual and domestic violence.
The Programs files document important conferences and gatherings sponsored and co-sponsored by NAWHERC, such as the HIV/AIDS Gatherings for Spiritual Leaders and Traditional Healers and the Native Women's Reproductive Rights Coalition which developed the Native Women's Reproductive Rights Agenda, and the Native Women's Leadership Training Program.
There are also a small amounts of RESTRICTED and OVERSIZE materials at the end of the collection.
Programs, Publications, and Studies and Reports files contain copies of final products and some research materials related to NAWHERC's impressive body of community-based research and its wellness publications.
The records give a good sense of NAWHERC's work in coalition with many other organizations through the administrative correspondence and organizations files.
As is often true of modern organizational records, NAWHERC's day-to-day operations and internal processes are less well-documented, though researchers can get a sense of the Center's ongoing activities through meeting notes and staff reports. Proposals and reports to funders and potential funders contain some of the best descriptions of NAWHERC programs.
Researchers should also consult the papers of NAWHERC's Executive Director, Charon Asetoyer.
Open with caveat: collection has not been fully processed and therefore may be somewhat difficult to use. Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies. Files on interns and staff which contain recommendations and evaluations are closed to research until January 1, 2037.
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
NAWHERC's founding Executive Director Charon Asetoyer began donating the records of the Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2006.
This collection is organized into thirteen series:
SERIES I. GENERAL, HISTORY, AND PHOTOGRAPHS (1987-2006)
SERIES II. NATIVE AMERICAN COMMUNITY BOARD (NACB) (1986-2005)
SERIES III. ADMINISTRATION (1988-2006)
SERIES IV. FINANCIAL MATERIALS (1987-97)
SERIES V. LAKE ANDES WOMEN'S LODGE (1990-91)
SERIES VI. ORGANIZATIONS (1987-2006)
SERIES VII. PROGRAMS (1987-2005)
SERIES VIII. PUBLICATIONS (1985-2008)
SERIES IX. STUDIES AND REPORTS (1988-2005)
SERIES X. SUBJECT FILES (1979 -2006
SERIES XI. YANKTON SIOUX TRIBE (1981-2005)
SERIES XII. RESTRICTED MATERIALS (1990-2005)
SERIES XIII. OVERSIZE MATERIALS (1984-2005)
Indian women -- Health and hygiene -- United States -- History -- Sources; Indian Women -- United States -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources; Indians of North America -- Health and hygiene -- History -- Sources; Indians Of North America -- South Dakota -- History -- Sources; Indians Of North America -- South Dakota -- Social conditions -- History -- Sources; Women's health services -- United States -- History -- Sources; Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center; Native American Community Board (Yankton Indian Reservation, S.D.); Yankton Indian Reservation (S.D.) -- Social conditions; Abused women -- Services for -- South Dakota; Reproductive health -- South Dakota; Public health -- United States -- History -- Sources; Reproductive rights -- United States -- History -- Sources; Family violence -- United States -- History -- Sources; Asetoyer, Charon
Related materials can be found in the Sophia Smith Collection in the Charon Asetoyer Papers, Rebecca Adamson Papers, and the records of the National Women's Health Network Records, Sistersong Women of Color Reproductive Justice Collective Records, Black Women's Health Imperative Records, National Latina Health Organization
A 2006 interview with NAWHERC Executive Director Charon Asetoyer is part of the SSC's Voices of Feminism Oral History Project. Transcript online at http://www.smith.edu/library/libs/ssc/vof/vof-intro.html
- SERIES I. GENERAL, HISTORY, AND PHOTOGRAPHS (1987-2006), .25 linear ft.
  This series provides an overview of NAWHERC and consists primarily of newspaper clippings and press releases. There are a few photographs including slides used in the Fetal Alcohol Syndrome program, images of gravesites near White Swan, and photographs from the Native Women's Reproductive Health and Rights Roundtable at the SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Rights Coalition conference in 2000.
- SERIES II. NATIVE AMERICAN COMMUNITY BOARD (NACB) (1986-2005), .5 linear ft.
  This series contains general information about the Native American Community Board, the parent organization of NAWHERC. Included are copies of the articles of incorporation and by-laws, job descriptions, policies and procedures, Board of Directors meeting minutes and notes, financial records, and a few program proposals from the early years of the Board.
- SERIES III. ADMINISTRATION (1988-2006), 1.5 linear ft.
  This series documents the administration and day-to-day operation of NAWHERC through such materials as calendars, correspondence, job descriptions, office forms, meeting and other notes, staff reports, and contracts and orientation materials related to the Victims of Crime Assistance (VOCA) and Volunteers in Service to America (VISTA) programs. There are also materials related to interns and a few NAWHERC events. The materials are arranged alphabetically.
- SERIES IV. FINANCIAL MATERIALS (1987-97), 1 linear ft
  Records in this series include correspondence with, and reports to, foundations and individuals who supported NAWHERC's work, as well as project and general funding proposals. The project proposals and reports to funders are especially rich sources of information about the Center's activities. There is a small amount of general information about funding sources and accounting practices at the beginning of the series. Additional information about NAWHERC's finances can be found in Series II. NATIVE AMERICAN COMMUNITY BOARD.
- SERIES V. LAKE ANDES WOMEN'S LODGE(1990-91), .25 linear ft.
  This series contains a small amount of general information about NAWHERC's shelter for victims of domestic abuse, the Lake Andes Women's Lodge. The bulk of the materials relate to the 1990-91 struggle to obtain a zoning variance to establish the shelter and NAWHERC's associated lawsuit against the City of Lake Andes.
- SERIES VI. ORGANIZATIONS (1987-2006), 3.5 linear ft.
  This series contains correspondence; newsletters; brochures and flyers; conference information; and a variety of other materials related to regional, national, and international organizations working on issues of interest to NAWHERC. These include HIV/AIDS, indigenous women, American Indian groups and tribes, environmental sustainability and stewardship, reproductive rights, and women's health. While many folders contain a small amount of basic information on the organization, more extensive materials can be found in the files on the Dakota Round Table, the Native Women's Reproductive Rights Coalition, SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Coalition, the South Dakota Coalition Against Domestic Violence, and the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services' Indian Health Service and Food and Drug Administration. To save stacks space, newsletters, circular letters, publications, and un-annotated Board Meeting packets which can be found elsewhere in the Sophia Smith Collection were returned to the donor. See the Provenance and Access section of this finding aid (below) for information about these related materials.
  The materials are arranged alphabetically.
- SERIES VII. PROGRAMS(1987-2005), 3.5 linear ft.
  This series contains correspondence, proposals, contracts, reports, meeting notes, curriculum and training materials, publications and drafts, and conference and workshop materials related to NAWHERC programs.
  The materials are arranged alphabetically by program name.
- SERIES VIII. PUBLICATIONS (1985-2008), .5 linear ft.
  This series contains brochures and fact sheets about NAWHERC and a variety of health and environmental issues, low literacy nutrition education materials produced under the auspices of the National Cancer Institute and the Wicozanni Wowapi Good Health Newsletter.
  Other publications can be found in Series VII. PROGRAMS and Series IX. STUDIES AND REPORTS.
- SERIES IX. STUDIES AND REPORTS (1988-2005), 1.25 linear ft.
  This series contains drafts, some correspondence and research materials, and final reports produced by NAWHERC regular and intern staff.
- SERIES X. SUBJECT FILES (1979 -2006), 2 linear ft.
  NAWHERC assembled files on many subjects of interest to its constituency and staff. Many of these materials were intended for a general audience and are widely available, such as US Public Health Service pamphlets about dental care. These were returned to the donor.
  Published materials specific to American Indians and other indigenous peoples, women's health, were retained.
  To save stack space, newsletters, circular letters, brochures and other published materials that can be found elsewhere in the Sophia Smith Collection were returned to the donor. Please consult "Related Materials" section of this finding aid
- SERIES XI. YANKTON SIOUX TRIBE (1981-2005), 1.5 linear ft.
  This series documents NAWHERC's work with, and relationship to, the Yankton Sioux Tribe particularly as relates to environmental issues, such as efforts to prevent construction of a local landfill; tribal jurisdiction, particularly as it relates to law enforcement policies and personnel; economic development; domestic violence; and the quality and safety of the Marty Indian School. Included are materials from several lawsuits, Yankton Sioux Tribe v. Gaffey (also known as the "Jurisidiction Case"), Yankton Sioux Tribe v. Corps of Engineers (also known as the "Remains Case") and the "landfill cases" South Dakota v. Greger, South Dakota v. Yankton Sioux Tribe, and Yankton Sioux Tribe v. Southern Missouri Solid Waste Management District and Southern Missouri Solid Waste Management District v. State of South Dakota.
- SERIES XII. RESTRICTED MATERIALS (1990-2005), .25 linear ft.
  There are two types of restricted materials: files on interns and staff, which contain recommendations and evaluations, and original audiovisual materials.
  The files on interns and staff are closed to research until January 1, 2037. After that time Researchers must sign an Access Agreement Form before using them.
  Original audiovisual materials are closed to research. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual materials for which there is no extant use copy should contact the Sophia Smith Collection to discuss options.
- SERIES XIII. OVERSIZE MATERIALS (1984-2005), .25 linear ft.
  Oversize materials consist of a Lake Andes, South Dakota, zoning map; newsletters and newspapers; posters from the Stop Smoking in Indian Country campaign, and unidentified and undated flip charts used in planning a conference.
Acronyms
DLRP = Dakota Language Revitalization Project
DOCIP= Indigenous Peoples' Centre for Documentation
ESF = Eagle Staff Fund, First Nations Development Institute
FAS = Fetal Alcohol Syndrome
FNDI = First Nations Development Institute
Ford Foundation Project = 2-year project to incorporate women of color issues & concerns into local, national, and international population and development agenda, Jun 1993-Jun 1995, also known as "US Women of Color Delegation"
ICPD = International Conference on Population and Development NGO Forum 94, Cairo, Egypt
IHS = Indian Health Service
NACB = Native American Community Board
NAWHERC = Native American Women's Health Education Resource Center
NAYPWP = Native American Young People's Wellness Program
PHS = Public Health Service, US Dept of Health and Human Services
PIPES = People in Prison Entering Sobriety
U.S. Women of Color Delegation [see Ford Foundation Project]
WGIP = Working Group on Indigenous Populations, World Health Organization
WOC = Women of Color
WOCCRHR = Women of Color Coalition for Reproductive Health & Rights (aka Women of Color Coalition)
YAC= Youth Advisory Council of the NAYPWP
YST = Yankton Sioux Tribe
- SERIES I. GENERAL, HISTORY, AND PHOTOGRAPHS
  - General and history
    - General 1988-2011, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - News clippings 1988-2005, undated (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Press release, 5 Jan 1995 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Photographs
    - Fetal Alcohol Syndrome Slide Program, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Grave site near White Swan, circa 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Native Women's Reproductive Health and Rights Roundtable, SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Rights Coalition 2000 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Unidentified, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- SERIES II. NATIVE AMERICAN COMMUNITY BOARD (NACB)
  - General 1986-95 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "Native American Community Board" paper by Marilyn Crovatin for POLS 670, 12 Dec 1995 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Articles of incorporation and bylaws 1986 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Job descriptions 1986-88, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Policies and procedures
    - General, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Personnel 1989, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Board of Directors
    - Rosters 2002 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Minutes 1986, 1989-2003 (Box 1, Folder 16-17)
    - Annual meeting, 18 Jan 1992 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence 1991-2005 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Financial materials
    - Employer ID number 1985-90 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Forms and procedures, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)